what's the best way to stay healthy in
the face of so much conflicting
nutrition information
well ideally you would go to the source
the gold standard the peer-reviewed
medical literature and read through the
stacks of the latest medical journals
but who's got time for that I do welcome
to the nutrition facts podcast I'm your
host Dr Michael Greger
today I answer common questions like
what's the ideal LDL cholesterol level
and uh what's going on when someone who
eats healthily but their blood sugars
are still out of control
ideal LDL depends on whether or not you
have been diagnosed with heart disease
if you have not a lifetime LDL well
actually a lifetime LDL under 100 should
protect you from heart disease however
if you didn't figure this out into
middle age and you're uh and your ldl's
uh too high and you're trying to get it
down to prevent heart disease then 70
would be the target if you already have
heart disease
um uh then the target draw in terms of
secondary prevention to prevent the
second heart attack drops down to like
30 to 50 or basically as low as possible
so wait a second could there be a harm
of having cholesterol too low we didn't
know until pcsk9 Inhibitors came out we
have these new biologic injectable drugs
which can drop people's cholesterol LDL
cholesterol into the single digits
still not seeing any problems with
hormone manufacturer like testosterone
and estrogen or
any other issues that have piled on uh
so only benefit as you go lower lower
um but we don't uh most people should
not need drugs to get their LDL down
they just need to cut out or cut down on
the three things that increase one's
cholesterol and that is saturated fat
found mostly in animal fats and junk
trans fats found almost exclusively now
in animal fat now that's been removed
from the food supply
um from a partial addressing into oils
and third is dietary cholesterol found
predominantly an X but throughout the
animal kingdom just do all that your
cholesterol should drop right down add
in a whole bunch of high fiber plant
foods which is say whole plant Foods
um and you can push your cholesterol
down even further
um yes in addition to eating healthy
there are a few Foods particularly that
may lower LP little a further I think
those are
um black cumin seed and um flax seeds
okay Jesse has natural dough um HDL with
a hover plant-based diet LDL
triglycerides plummeted fantastic but
um the talks about a triglyceridatio
ratio what's important a number to track
LDL is an important number to track we
used to think HDL so-called good
cholesterol was good and actually had
benefits in terms of reducing disease
risk it turns out that is not the case
uh based on a whole range of evidence
um including drugs that um that raise
HDL which actually had to be stopped
earlier because it was killing people
and probably most importantly the
so-called mendelian randomization
studies were people who just genetically
at Birth born
um with genes that give them kind of
unnaturally elevated SEO throughout
their entire lives regardless what they
eat or how they live
um do not actually have lower
cardiovascular disease however
those born with high LDL die early
because from cardiovascular disease and
those were low LDL are protected from uh
heart disease regardless of what they
eat
um proving that uh uh effectively proven
of course we can actually there's
actually real proving proving in terms
of randomized controlled trials but um
it's the best um in terms you get for
observational data
um which um so the LDL is actually a um
a risk factor not just a correlate so
don't worry about your HDL worry about
your LDL and it's wonderful that they're
down and uh that's fantastic
congratulations
okay Francis says what is the main
reason why one's A1C fluctuates from
high to low and high to low for those of
you who are like what is an A1c
um it is a measure of kind of long-term
blood sugar control over the last few
months or so
um but really uh biased towards kind of
more recent events and so the main
reason is people are
um eating different foods and
um although women can get hormonal
changes throughout the month
um that even if they're eating the same
thing they can have different blood
sugar responses so that could be one
reason
um and uh you know if you're sick uh you
know you have really high blood
pressures
um uh even if you're kind of eating
healthy but typically
um we tend to think of HBA A1C as
um in terms of diabetic control and how
well medications are working
um and for pre-diabetes or uh in general
um it's uh typically uh um what's
happening with a diet uh primarily the
glycemic load of different foods and so
I encourage people to cut out uh refined
grains
um and things that cause too high of a
blood sugar Spike
okay santanu says the fan base diet
reduced sugar substantially I want to
know how do I reduce insulin resistance
great um but if you want to reduce
um your insulin resistance
um you decrease the cause of insulin
resistance which is excess saturated fat
intake in the context of a hyper caloric
diet
um or excess visceral adiposity if you
um if your waste uh measure your belly
button is more than half your height you
need to lose weight to reduce that
visceral fat and decrease insulin
resistance regardless of what you eat
okay BLK says type 2 diabetic oh but
eating healthy wonderful not on meds
fantastic oh but can't get glucose under
control
um and so uh one of the reasons maybe
you're still uh you're suffering insulin
resistance from excess visceral fat
um so if you have excess abdominal fat
um I can spill fat in your bloodstream
and so even if you don't have
um it going into your mouth you still
have these high levels of fat in your
blood and that um interferes with um
insulin responsiveness in your muscles
and liver
um and that's what causes
um type 2 diabetes especially when it
offloads fat to your poor pancreas and
can destroy some of your insulin
producing cells
um and so weight loss would be the next
step and if your glucose is not under
control you should
um indeed
um I talked to your doctors about being
on meds until
um something like metformin until uh you
can get it under control with dye it
though it may take weight loss to drop
your visceral fat to levels where your
insulin resistance drops enough that you
can reverse your diabetes
we would love it if you could share with
us your stories about Reinventing Your
Health through evidence-based nutrition
good nutritionfacts.org testimonials we
may be able to share it on our social
media to help Inspire others
to see any graph starts Graphics images
or studies mentioned here please go to
the nutrition facts podcast landing page
there you'll find all the detailed
information you need plus links to all
the sources we cite for each of these
topics for our Vital timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics you can
order the ebook audiobook or hard copy
of my latest book how to survive a
pandemic
for recipes check out my new how not to
diet cookbook it's beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes for delicious
and nutritious meals and of course all
the proceeds are received from the sales
of all my books go to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a non-profit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest in nutrition research via
bite-sized videos and articles
everything on the website is free
there's no ads no corporate sponsorship
no Kickbacks it's strictly
non-commercial not selling anything I
just put it up as a public service as a
labor of love as a tribute to my
grandmother whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition